I think it was two years ago that I
released a video going over a couple of
studies on uriththna, a metabolite
produced by our gut microbiome. Now, it
was brought up that uriththna is only
produced by a minority of people because
not everyone's gut microbiome is capable
of producing the molecule. However, when
supplementing with uriththna directly,
the argument went that it improves
aspects of health like V2 max strength,
osteoarthritis, and more. and across
multiple measures that seems to be the
case. Even so, I wasn't bullish on
uriththna for reasons that I'll get into
later. Now, however, a new study
released that shows effects against age
related immune decline. So, has my tune
changed toward the positive? Is
uriththna now a worthy supplement
investment? Well, this study certainly
indicates multiple areas where ur
uroliththan aid does lead to effects in
humans. According to this newly minted
randomized control trial, their focus
was on change in the immune system. As
the immune system changes in multiple
ways as we get older from reduced
numbers of immune cells to protect our
body to greater inflammation as our
common known as innate immune system
shifts towards aggressiveness and
pro-inflammation on a more consistent
and unwanted basis. So when people in
their 50s, men and women are given
uriththna or a placebo for just one
month, what changes can we expect? And
are these changes of any real benefit?
The answer to the first question is yes,
we see changes. To the second, I am far
less convinced. Now, I [snorts]
mentioned there are reduced numbers of
immune cells as we age. And one of those
major groups of immune cells are called
CD8 TC cells. They're highly destructive
specialized immune cells. Think of them
like special forces or green berets or
the French Foreign Legion. You get the
idea. They're given one objective and
they are highly specialized to destroy
the pathogen causing illness. Now, as we
age, the number of these cells,
especially naive cells, so meaning cells
that have not been given instructions to
destroy, so no orders have been filed,
is reduced. This leaves us more
vulnerable to viruses, bacteria and
actually also things like cancer. So
when uriththna is consumed by people, we
actually see an increase in the number
of these specialized important cells
seen here. The higher the dots and the
lines, the more of these CD8 tea cells
are present. Now in green on the left we
have the cells of the people on the
eriththnne and on the right we have the
date of the people on the placebo. Now
statistically speaking there is a
significant difference with those
consuming uriththna experiencing a b
beneficial rise. So the main point here
being that uriththna improves the
vitality and the number of our
specialized immune cells. And in fact
other cells especially cancer killing
cells like natural killer cells are also
elevated in number when people consume
uriththna. Interestingly this does not
translate to all cell types. One of the
touted benefits of uriththna from
previous research has been related to
its mitochondrial effects. The good old
powerhouse of the cell as they say. Now
previous research has indicated that
uriththna impacts mphagy the clearance
of mitochondria as well as increasing
the signals for mitochondrial production
called biogenesis. So might this also
happen in our immune cells? The more
mitochondria, the more metabolic
flexibility by ourselves. So
mitochondrial biogenesis is controlled
by a master protein within our cells
called PGC-1 alpha. This protein, this
transcription co-activator, which
essentially means that it works in
unison with other signaling proteins
within our cells and encourages the cell
to produce the proteins necessary to
create new mitochondria. So when we
consume uriththna there's an increase in
this protein this PGC1 alpha it's pretty
brilliant. So while not a direct measure
of mitochondria we have evidence that
uriththna raises a powerful
mitochondrial growth signal in our
immune cells. This same study also
indicated an anti-inflammatory effect of
uriththna supplementation as well. So
this all sounds pretty great and clearly
we don't just see changes, we see
benefits seemingly abound from
uriththna. Now I'd like to discourage
you from using uriththna. Yeah, you
heard that right. Discourage you. I'm
going to present an argument against
using it and I'll tell you how much is
used across the studies if you still
choose to use it as there's people who
actually swear by it. like this comment
that I received in my last analysis. And
if you think that you'd also get benefit
or you just I don't know want to learn
more about it like its effects against a
cancerpromoting protein called tox or
how it stacks up against another
molecule that I'm a much bigger fan of
or its V2 effects and much much more
then consider joining the physionic
insiders. You'll get both of my full
analyses on uraliththna in video form
along with full articles. Plus, you can
search my approved supplement list. And
you get a researcher that dissects the
data for you and assesses and explains
the quality and strength of the evidence
of all kinds of different health topics
for you with actionable takeaways. Plus,
all these perks right here. It's a
steal, I tell you. The link to join the
Physionic Insiders is in the
description. So yes, we went over three
instances here. Urithna is a benefit. It
promoted an anti-inflammatory state. It
increases the number of specialized
immune cells that decline with age. It
promotes a powerful mitochondrial
production protein. And even so, my
critique two years ago still stands just
as strongly, if not stronger than
before. Generally when I'm assessing the
importance of a substance in this case
the supplement uriththna I'm looking at
a number of studies the quality of the
studies and what effects that the
molecule has in those studies. So the
evidence is mounting in favor of
urolithna as we now have multiple
randomized control trials that indicate
benefits across a number of areas of
health. That means that the number of
studies and the quality of the studies
have increased over time which is an
excellent argument for using uriththna.
However, the effects of uriththna are
not as impressive as they seem. I say
that from multiple perspectives.
One, the measurements are usually not
functional endpoints. I'm making up an
example, but if the claim is that
uriththnache helps against arthritis,
most people want to know if they'll, I
don't know, feel less pain and be able
to move more normally. These are
functional outcomes. However, the
studies done so far are typically
focused on mechanisms and showing
improvements in genes related to
osteoarthritis.
It's not a bad thing, but it isn't
exactly worldchanging. or when function
is assessed, the effects are very mild,
as in yes, they are statistically
significant, but they are small changes.
For example, in a previous study that I
went over, I'll link my previous
analysis for you, they measured the
strength of one part of the leg, and
they showed a singledigit improvement.
Or if you look at what we went over more
closely, like the data that I presented
to you here, you might notice that the
absolute change is less than 1%. In
addition, it's a change compared to the
placebo condition, not against baseline,
where the result was probably nothing.
The comparison they used is the better
one, but it doesn't change the fact that
these effects are small. The point being
although benefits are shown with
uriththna supplementation the benefits
are just very small. So then is it an
absolute no for uriththna? Not
necessarily. We know it has an effect
assuming that we can trust the studies
as most if not all are funded by a
uriththna supplement company and many of
the researchers are employees of said
company and if we still accept it as
that it has positive effects. We do know
that it helps across a number of health
metrics, not just immunity. So, it has a
widespread effect, which is a good
argument. In addition, the studies are
short. So, could the effects continue to
grow if used for 6 months, a year,
several years? We don't know. But it's a
perfectly reasonable possibility. Could
it be effective for people who don't eat
the healthiest microbiome beneficial
diet? maybe it would be more beneficial
for them than what we see here.
Absolutely. So, just because I'm not a
big fan still, which could change as
more research emerges, that doesn't
actually mean that arguments can't be
made in favor of uriththna
supplementation.
Okay, doc, break it down into simple
terms for me and shut up with all the
waffling back and forth. We see that
uriththna has a mild effect in improving
our immune profile. Uralithna has
effects across many health issues, but
the benefits are often very small and
likely not worth the money for most. If
you choose to supplement, the effective
dose used in the studies is 1,000
milligrams per day. If you want to learn
more on uriththna, join my insiders
program. I'll be discussing it on the
next podcast, exclusive for the
insiders, or check out this video on my
other analysis. Hope this helped you
make some decisions and I'll catch you
in the next one. Bye.